In a AI digital age, energy capacity
equals economic capacity. Why build a
new data center and buy the million GPUs
if I can't power them? You're going to
see more and more defaults happening on
many of those data center projects cuz
the energy won't be there.
>> Whenever you have the technology to make
something easy, that means the
bottleneck moves somewhere else.
>> Nothing's a chip anymore. It's a rack.
It took me 3 months to design it, but
it's 9 months until I can actually start
to use it. Exactly. How many major new
memories have we had over the last 30
years?
>> Zero.
>> Memory innovation for the first time in
30 years is nigh upon us. I declared the
death of copper about 25 years ago.
Eventually, I'll be right for all of us
hardware guys. This is like renaissance
in front of us. AI inference accelerator
chips. And I'm sure I don't even know
them all. Why are you guys funding so
many of those?
>> You funded your fair share, too.
>> Historically, there have not been a 100
competing processor vendors in any
industry ever. This is a temporary
thing. It'll converge back to a view.
>> I see it as a
>> I'm here with uh our esteemed guest and
dear friend and former boss, Mr. Pat
Gellinger. Welcome Pat. Pat is currently
the general partner at uh at Playground
Global, but uh as uh you're very very
well known in the industry for leading
Intel, for being the CTO of Intel, of
course, leading VMware and many other
things.
>> So, welcome.
>> Hey, thank you, Rayu. Great to be with
you and Guido, right? And to me, this
feels just a little bit like old home,
right? You know, it's like, you know,
you know, it was like uh we superimposed
a year of change, right? But uh you both
look the same. I feel uh energetic. So
let's dive in.
>> There has never been a day when you
stopped being energetic. So there no
news there. Uh but yeah. No, let's start
actually from uh from your Intel career,
right? I mean recently Andre Horovitz
created this Horowitz and recreent
academy
>> which was to find talented people
between 16 and 22 and then put them into
a a modern educational setting so they'd
be well prepared for either doing things
on their own or joining the companies of
today. You had a similar experience like
you went to a regular trade school and
then jumped into Intel.
>> Yeah. Yeah. When we were what 18 or 19
is
>> Yeah. Uh, you know, it was really a sort
of magical period. You know, I'm 16
years old. I accidentally win a
scholarship. I go to tech school, right?
Skipped my last year and a half of high
school and Intel comes recruiting when
I'm 18 years old. And, uh, you know, I
never been on an airplane. Uh, had
already fallen in love with computers at
tech school. And, uh, the interviewer,
right, Ron Smith was his name. He writes
on his page. And I was number 12 that he
interviewed that day. And if you've
interviewed 12 people in a row, you
can't tell male from female, you know,
by the end of it, right? You know, I'm
number 12. He says, "Smart, aggressive,
arrogant. He'll fit right in." So, I got
invited to go, you know, come to uh
Intel and, you know, just became uh, you
know, really uh glorious. uh you know
starting as a technician moved into the
design team at the end of the 286 you
know engineer number four on the 386 you
know uh architect and design manager for
the 486 all of that while doing my
master my bachelor's my masters and PhD
work so it was like the the the best
career that you could possibly have
you're learning by you know day and
you're putting it to practice at night
and
>> that's right that's right you're
creating new completely new era of chips
for I bet most of what you learned
and what you built there was a big gap
because you're breaking new ground.
>> Yeah. In a lot of ways and uh you know
really was a pretty incredible time in
the industry and I remember you know one
of the professor classes uh you know he
uh postulated a new carry look ahead
adder design right in one of my classes
at Stanford. So I said well I'm working
on the 386 carry look ahead adder so let
me go try it. So I come back two days
later to the professor and I said it
doesn't work right and I started
argument with my you know professor at
Stanford and it was like you know it was
like what you know the next two class
periods were just me and the professor
arguing over why his design didn't work.
>> He had a book that was being published
what that design is. So he was he was
very annoying. It was very time
sensitive for him
>> and you know we started builtin self
test right you know and I remember Ed
McCcluskey at Stanford was my professor
and he was sort of the father of that
and we you know had wonderful arguments
around why most of his ideas were bad
they weren't practical for real chips
but I was putting you know builtin self
test to work on the 36 you know John
Hennessy uh you know was my thesis
advisor and obviously he did okay I say
you know I helped his career he became
president and he's done okay since then
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Later on we'll talk about the CIS versus
risk debate, but I want to talk about
the 486. Sorry. Go ahead.
>> I had the same experience when I was
teaching at Stanford. You know, you you
come with something that you think is
the truth and then the student comes
that works in industry is like, well,
actually not quite. So, you know, the
next lecture you come back with like,
okay, uh, I looked this up. You're
right. You know, this is this is
outdated.
>> Yeah. And I tell you, you know, that's
part of the set of students. Yeah. that
interaction and I think that's part of
what makes Silicon Valley so unique.
Yeah.
>> Right. You know is you have you know
these so many companies and you know
entrepreneurship it's like in the water
here right you know starting things up
and new ideas and challenging the
professors and you can't be a professor
at a place like Stanford and not expect
to get challenged and enjoy it.
>> There's a good foot traffic in and out
of that ivory tower.
>> Yeah I think it's good.
>> Yeah. Now 486 was your big
>> Yeah.
>> accomplishment if you will. Obviously
lots of people worked on it. Um
and you guys broke some new ground in
chip design there, right?
>> Mhm.
>> And um increased what functions the chip
was supposed to do and so on and so
forth.
>> Yeah. It was a pretty magic period uh as
well because it was before what you
would think of as the EDA industry.
>> Oh wow. Yes, that's right. and uh you
know the the end of the a little bit of
the 386 but the 486 was really the first
chip to implement what what you would
think of as modern EDA techniques. Yeah,
we did a highle design, right? Uh
description and RTL description, but
there was no vera log.
>> So, we invented HDL, right? The Intel
hardware description language. So, you
know, I wrote my own language. Well, you
had to build a compiler for that
language, right? You know, so we created
the compiler for the language. There was
no automatic place in route, you know.
So, we had to invent that. And we worked
with Alberto Sanji Yavanji Vincentelli
at Berkeley and some of his students for
the first you know placement the first
routing the first automated timing you
know management and
>> so they created EDA to some degree. to a
great degree that uh you know and that
was really one of the hallmarks that not
only was the 486 you know this
compatible you know pipeline
microprocessor but we ushered in you
know many of the foundations of what
became the modern EDA uh industry and
you know it was really you know pretty
magical period of the industry.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So if you look at today
>> Yeah. Will people look back as Blackwell
and saying you know this was of the last
generation that was was done before AI
took over the design process for for
micros are we in a similar transition
right now
>> I think there are certainly aspects of
that and uh you know I think you know
when you look at you know things like
jalapeno today right you sort of say you
know that you know that's that's sort of
a first principles use of AI in the chip
design process right where you throw out
a lot of those things now you know un
You know there are pieces of design that
are still really hard right uh in that
sense and a lot of the analog right
aspect certis is probably the best
example of that you know are still not
aiable right you just need lots of
silicon data right to get those so you
either get so conservative in your
analog design you know that you're able
to I'll say AI it uh or right you got to
do those the hard way uh you know for
but to now many of the logic functions
can really be done with uh AI tools and
techniques in pretty incredible ways,
right? Your transistor budgets are big
enough, the design tools are getting
smart enough, you know, a few experts
guiding the tools and how to apply it.
And I really think it will be somewhat
like the 46 that way, right? Where you
sort of look back and say, "Yep, that
was the beginning of a new era of chip
design."
>> Whenever you have the technology to make
something easy, that means the
bottleneck moves somewhere else.
>> Yeah. Can we guess at this point where
the bottleneck will be in the future?
>> There's some things which it seems like
AI is incredibly good at, right? Like
creating the software layers, you know,
writing kernels, um, you know, a lot of
the
>> I think a lot of the sort of being able
to specify the the the objectives at a
higher level which then gets sort of
translated into very log right and so
what is the new frontier? What is the
thing that that will be difficult going
forward? Well, you know, when you look
at today, you know, so let's say, you
know, Guido and Pat, we're off to do a
great new chip together. We're building,
>> right? You know, right? You know, and
it's the one that's going to leap ahead
because we have understanding of 8646,
>> you know, we have understanding of the
AI workloads. We have understanding then
of how to compose that into the right,
multiply, accumulate, you know, register
structures,
>> the perfect visibility model workloads
of tomorrow as well,
>> you know, and all of that kind of stuff.
And you know let's say you know we turn
our AI you know tools loose we are great
within three months we have an awesome
design right you know you know for that
we've been a little bit conservative on
all the analog components of it
>> you know now we still have like a couple
of really major bottlenecks today you
know one is right we still have nine
months of silicon processing time
>> right you know someone like that right
so I can design the thing in three
months but I can't actually get it into
real silicon at scale for 9 months.
Okay, that sucks, right? So, we have to
really see that bottleneck improve if
we're going to have this innovation
because we know that
>> about the validation verification stages
or even beyond that. Well, you know,
first I can't get anything out of fab.
Yeah. You know, in less than three
months and that's if I have, you know,
like supercharged design flows, right?
So, I said, you know, you know, how do I
compress that, right? Uh, you know, for
it and then I got to get into advanced
packages. 3D packages are getting
complex. So, that's like another three
months, right? You know, and then I have
to put it into a rack scale solution
because nothing's a chip anymore. It's a
rack, you know. So we're 9 months, you
know, it took me 3 months to design it,
but it's nine months until I can
actually start to use it, you know. So
how do we start to compress, you know,
those aspects of design? And I think we
need new forms of lithography, you know,
to enable that. We need, you know,
design flows that don't require, you
know, $50 million of mass cost until I
can get things into prototyping. So you
know, to me, how do you compress that to
a month or two, right? Because I can now
do the design in three months. How can I
have that done in a month or two?
Because if it takes me a year and a half
until I actually get scale and software
on it,
>> okay, my understanding of the AI
workloads is no longer applicable to the
chip that I designed.
>> Right. You know, so you know, all of
those
>> you see that play out live right now
with AI. Yeah.
>> Right. You said, you know, it's almost,
you know, we can look at it
historically. It was like, you know,
Graph Core wasn't a bad design, but the
world moved on,
>> right? and you know uh in that. So all
of those aspects somewhat obviate the
fact that AI has made the design piece
easy. All of those manufacturing scale
issues to me become a huge bottleneck.
Right. Another bottleneck of course is
memory.
>> Yep.
>> Right. You know memory bandwidth
>> we noticed. Yeah.
>> Right. And you know for that as I've
described HBM is a hideous memory. It's
just the best one that we
>> ask you about that. Yes.
>> You know it's a terrible memory. You
know I get terrible bit density. I'm
limited to shoreline bandwidth the power
right uh issues thermal issues DRAM
doesn't like to be hot
>> concentrating everything in one spot
>> you know it's terrible to give
>> that AI is a memory compute workload yes
>> right so right you know for that so I
you know I need to you know compress
that development uh and embodiment into
real scale you know I need to fix memory
>> right uh associated with So to me that's
another critical bottleneck for us to
attack. Uh and uh power right you know
power in you know thermal uh and most of
the power simulation aspects today are
bad
>> right you know you don't have good 3D
modeling tools for power power
dissipation hotspots uh etc. you know my
voltage in right you know I'm
essentially guard banding almost my full
power envelope correct
>> right so essentially I'm losing you know
40% of my power and guard banding so I
got to get much better at power modeling
you know and then my power dissipation
techniques are bad right so you know
>> delivery model has to change too
>> yeah so all of these things you know to
me those are the you know the next big
bottlenecks right you know how do I you
know improve each one of those and now
right you know if I've done that Okay,
now we're on to an exciting era for
what's next. So, you know, thank you for
those great AI tools, but you know, I
got big challenges even when those are
fully deployed.
>> And so,
we've seen sort of a rebirth in the
number of chips and chip architectures
and so on and so forth.
>> Yeah.
>> Thanks to these workloads.
>> Yeah. It's like there's a 100 AI
inference accelerator chips and I'm sure
I don't even know them all.
>> Yeah, exactly. Yeah. So, so
>> why are you guys funding so many of
those anyway?
>> You funded your fair share too.
>> Yeah. So, um, so are we, you know,
they're all to their credit making
different design assumptions either in
the components that you talked about or
>> in the
>> in the part of the para curve that
they're targeting. So do you think
there's room for all of these or are we
in a world where partly because of what
Guido talked about AI tooling
um we now have the ability to build more
different kind of chips.
>> Yeah.
>> And the time is enormous whichever way
you want to even more provocatively
historically there have not been a 100
competing processor vendors in any
industry ever right. So
>> is this a more heterogeneous future?
Will we see is this a temporary thing?
It'll converge back to a view.
>> Yeah. And you know, I see it as a more
temporary thing and it will converge is
is what I expect. And there's probably
three different reasons that I see that
to be the case. You know, one of them
is, you know, this emerging
heterogeneity that you see in the
compute uh environment where okay, now I
have specialized prefill versus decode.
Well, you know, and now people are
saying, well, we really need a
specialized tier for midfill, not just
prefill, right? You know, so now I have
early prefill and now I have midfill,
which is, you know, differential.
>> Maybe speculate and verify if we listen
to OpenAI here, right?
>> Yeah. You know, and you know, all of a
sudden my compute fleet becomes more and
more granular across the workload. And I
think anytime that you've seen that in
history is not sustainable. And then all
of a sudden right when you know as you
look at that and now people are saying
well as I go to reasoning models I want
something that looks more like a CPU
again. So you know all of a sudden I
didn't want that level you know that
didn't become the predominant portion of
my compute capacity. I needed more of it
over here, right? and model and model
workflows and you know so on you know so
I really don't like I'll say at scale
specialization right because I think the
workloads are going to continue to
moderate you know and migrate so
significantly first you know second is I
think today's models are about to go
through some evolutionary breakthroughs
as well right you know I think the LLM
is sort of reaching the limits and now
as people look to how do I really model
3D right you know where you a flattish
LLM doesn't work well when you go to
molecules and chemicals and you know
imaging you know so I think we'll see
limits of that that'll cause different
shifts in the algorithmic domain I also
think that uh some of the most
interesting workloads become where you
start you know I'll say bringing HPC
like things back into AI like things
where all of a sudden you know 64-bit
provision uh precision counts again
right so I see
>> what would be an example of that
>> well you know imagine that my AI model
is now inducing the five most
interesting domains for a chemical
analysis,
right? Okay, those chemical algorithms
are going to run with high precision,
right? You know, when you know which is
going to be the dominant piece of the
workload, right? Getting to the five
algorithms I need to run or running the
five algorithms, right, on different
chemical or biological systems. So you
know I do think that uh you know or as
we optimize our AI systems they will
lead us back to some of the things that
have been more traditional high
performance computing. So I see that
aspect of workload uh as well. So you
know all of that said is you know this
extreme specialization to me in the
compute architect I I sort of don't like
it because I don't think it's going to
be what the workloads will look like 2 3
four years from now. So that's one
reason I don't see all of these AI chips
as they get more and more specialized
for portions of the compute workload to
necessarily be right you know second is
right there's like a hundred of them now
>> right you know there's multiple optical
ones there's probabilistic ones and so
on and you know they're not all going to
win and they're not all going to win
because at the end of the day you have
to get scale
>> on these things and scale requires you
know you have to win you have to get
capital you have to get workloads onto
it so I think it sort of defies logic
that you're going to have a hundred of
these things. So I see them you know
coming back uh as a results of you know
simple you know capital market share
etc. you know which are the winning
teams you know winning designs winning
architecture so I see the workload
driving that you know I see the natural
you know industry consolidations you
know that will occur and then I also
expect that the winners will pick some
winners
>> right you know where you know an open AI
an Nvidia anthropic will say I like this
one because it isn't just hardware it's
how do the hardware and software code
evolve Yeah,
>> right. You know, for it and I do expect
that there's going to be h, you know,
here's this 10 I could pick for this. I
like that one. And it does require
investment in the software and the
workload evolution to take advantage of
those platforms. So for those three
reasons, yeah, we're going to see, you
know, a narrowing of the field uh in
that sense
>> and the deployment complexity as well.
Sorry, go ahead.
>> I mean, makes total sense and I think I
agree in most point. Let me still try to
stir a little bit controversy here just
to to stirring controversy to you guys
have changed it right
>> so so obviously 100 companies won't
access consolidate right and and
completely agree with your argument that
at the end of the day the large
consumers will pick winners to some some
degree right today I think
>> to be a first tier chip startup to some
degree whether you you're that or not is
defined by how much fraction you have
with with the with the really big Nice.
That said, um, and there's of also an
argument to say like, look, in any kind
of transition period, you probably have
a bit more of an explosion of different
approaches over time that that'll shake
out.
>> Now, all that said, I think there's an
argument you can make that basically
says, look,
>> historically, we standardized on, you
know, one or two architectures because,
you know, different instruction sets
were hard. we had to build multiple
compilers you know like the this
basically um this the the software
complexity dictated that you can only
have a certain small number of hardware
platforms
>> that part seems to be changing with AI
right today you know writing an
optimized kernel for I mean I think was
a great example where they basically
said look humans can't really program
this thing anymore but an agent swarm
overnight can do it that's all we need
right so where basically you can say
like if you can build a chip that has a
certain capability it's now much much
easier to build the software layers on
top that fully leverages that could a
result of that be that we have a little
bit more hetrogenity just because the
you know it's it's easier to program
that hetrogenity going forward
>> and and I I do think it changes some of
you know you you know the you know where
the bottleneck lands right changes in
that regard you know the first
bottleneck is the one I'd point to that
we've already talked about still takes a
year and a half to build these things
>> right you know and then the second
bottleneck is not only does it take a
year and a half to get these things into
racks the scales and so on like that now
to make them useful full. Okay. Well,
could I borrow 50 billion, right? I
mean, you're not talking about small
capital expenditures. You're talking
about very large capital expenditures
and data centers, you know, power, you
know, commitments and so on like that.
Well, I got to build this thing at
scale, right, associated with it. So,
and that's going to defy a lot of
heterogeneity uh as a result. Now, you
know, clearly big players and we saw
this with what, you know, Nvidia did
with Grock, okay? you know, we're gonna
sort of own some of that heterogeneity,
right? And you know, you know, two years
from now, you're not going to tell what
Grock is inside of Nvidia, right? It's
just going to be like another, right?
You know, someone like that. So, you'll
see the architectures, you know, sort of
hide the heterogeneity, right? Uh inside
of it, which to me is just fine, right?
You know I mean that's what layering
that's what abstraction has always done
associated with it you know but I think
those forces are powerful ones to I'll
say expose
a lot of the heterogeneity no right I
think it will get abstracted underneath
you know some of these but at the end of
the day it's still hard to build these
things at scale
>> earlier you talked about HPM being
hideous memory
>> by far the best one we have today.
>> Exactly. It's like the thing about
democracy.
>> Um,
we can't recall when there was the last
memory innovation. It might have been
obtained. I think you probably had
something to do with it.
>> Yeah, that one died. So,
>> that one died.
>> We killed it.
>> Yeah, we killed it. We killed it.
>> So,
do you think memory innovation
is around the corner or what needs to
happen for obviously we understand the
scale problem because it's even more
>> Yeah.
>> larger there.
>> Yeah. But if you keep the scale aside
even from a technology point of view.
>> Yeah. And let's you know uh you know
look at that history. I've probably
personally been associated with at least
five different new memory architectures.
Optane just being one of them right you
know that did not see the light of day
right uh as well. Uh I'm probably
familiar with close to a hundred that
have happened in the industry over the
last 30 years. And exactly how many
major new memories have you had over the
last 30 years?
>> Zero.
>> Right. You know, which you know, okay.
DRAM, SR, RAM, flash. Okay. What else is
there? D RAM, SRAM, flash. Yeah. You
know, so I I do think
>> flash stacking console a little bit.
>> Barely. Yeah. Right. You know, but
anyway. Right.
>> So, uh, you know, in that it it you
know, it has been right you know, a a
disappointing
>> that we haven't created, you know, the
next physics. Yeah. that enable you know
lowcost high performance resilient
manufacturable memory right you know for
it so I do think and and now and and
over the last 30 40 years you know
memory was a terrible industry
>> right because you would make money one
year and then you lose money for the
next four right so let's go do R&D in an
industry that makes money one out of
five years right you know it's just
always you know it's just been so
terribly difficult because it's been
such driven by such violent
commoditization cycles.
>> That has changed a little bit though
recently
>> over the last 5 years.
>> Happy days, man.
>> So So all three big memory vendors are
on the in the top 20 most valuable
companies on the planet.
>> Yeah, that's a crazy change, isn't it?
>> Oh, it's just so right. you know who who
would have thought right uh associated
with it and anybody who looks at the AI
workloads and it's always you know it's
much harder to you know you know it's
easy to predict the past but it's a
little bit harder to predict the future
right and you know in that you look at
it and say AI is a memory role
>> exactly
>> right you know inside of it so I think
there is the combination of capital and
technology needs that will justify
memory innovation now there's two
domains things that I'm excited about uh
you know for it you know one is you know
this idea you know I do think that the
shoreline bandwidth limitations of HBM
is a fundamental issue
>> right so with that the idea you know and
obviously you know we have a company
Dmatrix that's doing this but I think
others will be you know whether it's you
know Cabbrris you know and their
techniques
>> the future is stacked yeah
>> somehow you got to bring memory and
>> in more ways than one
>> you know you got to bring memory and
compute together
>> right you know in a fundamental until uh
new structures. Um I do think that uh
given the workload now has such capital
being deployed against it you know in
the AI space that I do think we'll
actually be able to break through some
of those physics challenges as well uh
as well. So I do believe and you know
I've just substited
a new memory company as well that's
still a stealth but uh you know you know
I'm quite excited about some of the
innovations that will occur in new
memories and you're going to see new
materials uh you know for memory people
you know a lot of people looking at
things like ferro electrics uh you know
finding non-capacitive you know uh
highdensity memories finding memories
that can you know be high performance
high density and stackable right but you
know thing you know people are looking
at uh lowcost uh flash you know for that
I'm not particularly enthusiastic about
that idea myself I think you know speed
and performance of the underlying cell
are somewhat problematic with a flash or
an MRAM structure you know but I do
think there's memory innovations are
coming for the first time in 30 years
and I do think that's going to be an
exciting space and you know we'll have a
couple of companies there I'm sure
hopefully we'll do a few of them
together
What do you think? Should we do Okay.
You know, but we'll we'll find some
things to do here. But I think memory
innovation for the first time in 30
years is nigh upon us.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> It's it's amazing what a couple of$10
billion of market cap. I don't even
know. You say a trillion. Okay. Sorry.
>> You know, I think the memory industry
has now increased by market cap by $2
and a half trillion dollars. That's
great. You know, over the last four
years,
>> I think that's about right.
That is Yeah,
>> we could have just invested there and
not done any forential stuff.
>> Yeah, exactly. Use your money. Um,
how long what's your view? Sorry, go
ahead.
>> Yes. To to expand a little bit on the
stacking part if you have to predict h
how quickly will our chips get get
taller? Is this going to be like, you
know, we're going to go to two and then
sit there for a while or will we have,
you know, the 16 layer sandwich, you
know, happily mixing logic, memory,
>> pulled down this
HPM is going down at Nvidia, but how how
do you see this evolve? Yeah, you know,
I think there's um um you know, the
problem with stacking, right, is now
essentially the value of the stack,
right, becomes greater as you go to
higher dimensionality of the stack,
which means the yield of any individual
layer in the stacking process has to
keep coming, you know, essentially it
can't go up linearly. Yep. Right. you
know, it has to go up exponentially and
improving the manufacturing and defect
characteristics in an exponential way.
You know, when you get to eight or 16
high stacks gets to be so so hard when
you run the math on that uh associated
with it. You know, your manufacturer
flows have to be so close to perfect.
>> Although you could see designs that take
into account a certain model cost like
we've seen it for like a long time for
two dimensions.
>> Yeah, of course. But remember that was
the nature of DRAM. they always have bad
block replacement and you know spare
lines and so on like that. So I'm not in
any way, right, you know, minimizing
that, but assuming you're doing that,
you still need the yields to be so good.
You know, if I have a cracked die, I
don't care how much resilience you've
built into it. You can't, you know, it's
a bad die, right? So, you know, those
kind, you know, uh, so as a result of
that, I'm not, you know, a crazy 16 32
stack, you know, kind of guy. I think
there's going to be, you know, nice
three, four, five stacks, you know, that
just end up sort of being the sweet
spot.
>> The mid-rises. Yeah. Yeah. Right. Uh you
know for and I and I expect for you know
part of its manufacturing part of its
complexity uh associated with it you
know where's those yield sweet spots
associated with. So that's sort of where
I think most things land. But even there
right you know so let's say I now have
you know I now have a great compute tile
right you know how big does that tile
need to be? I mean everything's become
reticle limited now right? you know hm
can I go to more chiplets that have
better yield characteristics you better
thermal you know and then you're going
to say I want a memory stack on that you
know is it a two stack memory a four
stack memory you know I don't see it
becoming an eight stack memory you know
so to me two or four sort of right you
know but then power delivery needs to
get integrated into that so that becomes
sort of another element and I want that
in the Z dimension right associated with
it because you know I want my power
rails coming into this as well
>> right and Then I need, you know, fairly
intelligent RDL layers to distribute
signals across that platform. So to some
degree, you know, my canonical thing is
already about eight layer thick when you
add up all of those pieces associated
with it. And I think that's about all
you can do, right? At least as we
understand manufacturing today. And then
of course you we expect optics to come
in. So you're going to have more 35
material structures, you know, that are
going to be closer to this complex
because I want, you know, my IO getting,
you know, essentially, you know, deeply
integrated into that construct as well,
you know. So my siliconentric pieces
need to get complemented by some of
these other 35 materials and how do I
get optical connectivity built into
this? How do I get power rails, you
know, built into that? You know, that is
a, you know, I'll say that is an
engineering feat. and a manufacturing
nightmare, right, to bring all of those
pieces. But that's where the physics is
taking us uh over time. So because of
that, you know, throwing a 16 high stack
and to me, you know, it's like that's
crazy. You know, a two or four high
memory stack, you know, I think that's
probably where the speed sweet spot will
be.
>> And you didn't talk about the thermal
dissipation
>> and new materials needed for that.
>> Yeah. And obviously there's going to be
a lot of, you know, you know, first
thing, right? You just can't have some
of the, you know, the physics hotspots
that you have today. So you have to be
more intelligent about how you use the
the heat and spread the heat. But you
know then you're going to be saying okay
how do I both get power in and dissipate
power out uh of those environments. And
by the way if I can you know de you know
get much more efficient power in at the
voltages I want with much better you
know power responsiveness and my voltage
regulation you know then I don't create
as much thermal chimneys.
>> Yeah. But I do have to think okay how do
I cool these things and you know what
role do new materials diamonds and other
things have been postulated as ways to
you know do a better job of the thermal
cooling how do I then have better you
know liquid cooling techniques and
others you know sitting right on it you
know with good thermal characteristics
so yeah you know uh you know we we
engineers are becoming plumbers right
>> exactly
yeah we got to worry about MEC the chip
scale
>> let me ask about an operate phenomenon
which is some people have said hey let's
get the memory off of the package and
just go all optical between the compute
and the memory and that'll give you more
degrees of freedom and more ways of
building things what's your view on that
as opposed to stacking that's other
extreme
>> yeah you know I think the more OEO right
uh interfaces that you have you know
it's you know you know optical to
electrical to optical to you know the
more of those that you demand in your
core compute complex you enmy is just
hard right uh in that sense and you're
always going to have losses associated
with it you know people are you know
working hard to come up with more clever
techniques to decrease you know both the
cost and the power right you know how
how much of the power am I wasting as I
go through my you know my DAX and uh you
know conversions so I'm not a fan of
those you know because I think it gives
you access to large pools of memory
right but I I burn a lot of power
getting there.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. And remember my you know the
essentially you know the phentojoules
per compute is now actually pretty
amazingly good. Right. The phentojlesw
per bit of communication is
comparatively a thousand times worse
right and if I'm spending that much to
go get to large pools of so I don't like
those approaches you know myself. I
think they somewhat defy the underlying
physics of the solution. I mean and then
there's sort of the other approach to
say like look can we actually integrate
compute and memory directly right shift
some of the compute into the memory it's
>> some of the pim approaches
>> yeah exactly right so what
>> what are your thoughts around that
>> I'm not a fan of those either right um
because I think workloads you know
because now I have to take my workload
and I have to like push these little
pieces of compute into the memory right
you know so that you know I don't need
as much bandwidth of memory coming into
my real compute Right? And that puts
constraints on workloads. And again, you
know, I could be wrong on this,
particularly some of the design
flexibility and the intelligence that we
can now bring, you know, through the the
design aspects. But most PIM ideas, you
know, have been around for 2530 years.
And I think 2530 years from now, they'll
still be hanging around, right? In that
sense, you know, give me great memory
bandwidth, you know, that I can have,
you know, high density, uh, high
performance, and get it close to the
real compute engines. I expect that's
going to be a more generalizable
solution across many and evolving
workloads over time.
>> Well, so we're still stuck with denser
and denser chips, more compute, more
logic, more power,
>> and much better IO.
>> Now, I am a I am a huge fan, right, of
opt, you know, moving to optics for all
IO function. Yeah. Right. You know, I
declared the death of copper about 25
years ago. Eventually, I'll be right.
>> You're still right. one day one day soon
uh I'll be right but I think is that a
you know to me all IO should go to
optical right you know but that core
compute memory complex no right
>> so when do you the first step for it
going um all optical is to scale up even
more so than scale out
>> what's your views on that
>> yeah you know and I think we're now
>> what would be the like the application
or the workload driver if you will Well,
I think the workload driver is the one
in front of us.
>> Okay.
>> Right. I mean, you know, today, you
know, our scaleup environments, we're
putting tons of copper, right? You know,
and essentially copper is becoming a
wave guide that's getting shorter and
shorter, right? And all of a sudden, you
know, to make my copper work at uh, you
know, 5 m is more expensive than making
optical work, right, at 100 meters,
right? You know, so you know, I think
the physics is driving us there today,
>> you know. And you know so if that's the
case Pat why haven't we moved there
already? Yeah it's a complex supply
chain that you know has never been
tested at scale and I think now you know
I think everybody is looking at you know
some form of NPO CPO etc you know in the
28 29 time frame because you know I
can't scale up to large radics you know
compute uh clusters for my scale up
environment without making that move.
So, you know, clearly Nvidia has uh
indicated that. I think everybody else
in the industry expects, you know,
that's the conversion point. You know,
in reality, I should have never built an
NVL72. You know, it's an engineering
marvel and it's a manufacturing
nightmare, right? You know, it took the
industry, you know, one extra year and a
half to digest that beast, right? And it
really is amazing that, you know, we're
able to get it to scale, you know, so
on. But you know that really proved that
had we had a more mature optical supply
chain, we'd be much more advanced today.
We'd be able to build better scale up
environments today, you know, better,
you know, power, better cost, better
energy. But we didn't have the maturity
of the optical supply chains to allow
that and those things are not trivial to
get resolved. There's a lot of work to
happen, but I think 28 29 is the year
>> capacity. Good. for CSS.
>> We we're probably gaining a lot of
experience how in package optics work in
networking, right? And and I think many
of that will translate nicely to to
>> GPU. I do think but all of a sudden, you
know, it's like, okay, these things have
to work, you know, at 10 million GPU
scale. Wow. Right. You know, it has to
fit in packages and, you know, there's
just a lot of things there, you know,
and many forms of optical don't like bad
thermals. Well, guess what? Bad thermals
is the nature of the game for it, you
know. So we have thermal problems to
deal with, you know, package integration
problems. We didn't have enough, you
know, laser capacity in the industry. So
a bunch of things, but I don't see
anything there fundamentals. It's just a
lot of hard work at this point to pull
all of those pieces together.
>> In terms of the network architecture,
will this also mean a switch towards
more circuit switch networks just
because, you know, you you can't scale
these these very fast optical networks
indefinitely? Well, you know, uh, you
know, I like, uh, you know, uh, Nick
Mune, you know, another Stanford
professor here, good friend of mine, you
know, as well, you know, I mean, you
know him a little bit also, uh, Guido,
you know,
>> was he adviser?
>> He was not the advisor.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, but, you know, to me, he
describes it well, you know, we built,
you know, uh, networks for to be able to
handle any packet going anywhere with no
knowledge of where it might go. When you
think about AI, you know, it's almost
exactly the opposite. Yes. Right. You
know, we're doing flows that are large
and predictable.
>> So, in that sense, just the very
description says, hm, that looks more
like a switch than like a packet.
>> So, I do think this confluence of moving
to optical, right? And, you know, having
a workload that is far more predictable,
manageable, you know, large and flow,
you know, to me, you know, I do see
that. Yeah, we will go all the way to
bringing optical into the compute
complex and we will go all the way to
OCS or some form of optical uh switching
you know with more predictable flows you
know I mean that is the right you know
architecture and then you sort of say is
that scale up or scale out and to some
degree
>> say it sort of dissolves the boundary
there
>> yeah right if my scale up is big enough
then yeah you know just saying okay
what's the radics of my scale up
environment and when do I want to hook
it up to other clusters that are really
big and to me that ends up being a
pretty beautiful answer uh you know to
the future but I'm looking at somebody
who's way more expert on this than
myself. So
>> no I I I look I always found scale up
versus scale up to some degree an
artificial distinction. You understand
where it comes from right is we're kind
of using different protocols one is
front end one is backend network and so
on. So right now practically speaking it
is a it is a big difference.
>> Yeah.
>> If you take a step back and look at it
from a system architecture perspective
it achieves the same goal you know with
slightly different flavors slightly
different protocols that over time I
think will converge.
>> Yeah.
>> I mean especially for the AI training
workload.
>> Yeah. Although I mean training and
inferences actually look fairly similar.
>> The inference corp is less of
>> Yeah. Now I'll go on a you know right.
Does your brain stop learning?
>> Yeah.
>> Right. you know you know when you know
by the way as another characteristic of
workload evolution I do think the you
know the separation of training and
inferencing is going to become you know
less so going forward not more so right
that's a little bit of the argument
against you know you know more and more
heterogeneous architectures is I think
continuous learning you know I think
there'll be algorithmic domains that
will say yes continuous learning you
know becomes the nature of the algorithm
where yeah I do want my inference
environment to be updating my model
weights because you know that's giving
me more and more refinement you know
evolution across you know uh workloads
moving into environments that are less
formalized training uh as well we'll
have smaller data sets in those
environments so you know I'm not sure
that's a
>> but the number of nodes you need in
order to be useful is a smaller diameter
for inference than than for training
that's what remains
>> today that's true
>> yeah yeah
>> I mean I I still think there might be a
role for hetrogenity coming from a
different angle which is Different types
of AI workloads require very different
underlying like some are more comput
limited some are more more memory
bandwidth if you have a small diffusion
workload or so right the optimal card
for that looks very different from you
know a top-of-the-line you know 15
trillion 15 sorry 15 trillion weight LLM
right that needs to operate at massive
scale right so it's I I think that that
might driveity if anything
>> yeah I I think there's some room for
that you know but I'd also say okay now
I'm talking about putting a million GPUs
to work in my data center, right? And
you say, well, you know, for that
particular diffusion workload, you know,
I should really put something optimized
this way, right? So, I'm now going to
start, you know, putting, you know, a
thousand of those in, right? And for
that workload, I need, you know, 2,000
of these in and, you know, for some, you
know, and all of a sudden, you know, you
don't get some of the, you know, the
flexibility of scale, right? that you
would say and you know how much does it
cost me to manage and upgrade and you
know connect and you know fault domain
you know all of those types of things
>> the agents will do up all the upgrades
so there's no longer a problem
>> yeah yeah yeah thank you everything gets
easy so good out there
>> yeah so fleet management is done um so
we talked about what compute memory
networking
power is the next one
>> yeah yeah yeah
>> and you touched upon it with vertical
delivery inside the chip
on the chip.
>> But
I mean there's 800 volt DC, there's
power delivery to the data center.
>> Um there's an entire ecosystem all the
way to
power generation and and
the sociopolitical dimensions of that
and so on and so forth.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> So where does innovation come in and
where does like its pure execution?
Well, you the you know and if we start
at you know uh first principles here you
know our our nation has done a terrible
job with this energy capacity right you
know and essentially we went for 10 to
15 years where essentially I was taking
coal offline at the rate I was adding
renewables and essentially the nation
was flatlined in terms of overall energy
capacity. Not good because in a AI
digital age energy capacity equals
economic capacity right so essentially
my economic capacity as a nation flat
for 15 years if you buy that thesis
right which I think is very you know
provable over the last 5 years I you
know we've seen this enormous influx
into just give me more capacity uh but
you know I think uh you know even with
that we've gone to maybe increasing our
national energy capac capacity 4% per
year
>> something like that
>> going from you know essentially 0 to one
right wow 4x
or hm 4% right so to me you know that
you know it's a bad situation so we just
need more energy capacity
>> uh for it so number one and obviously we
have some companies in that space you
know we talked about nuclear operating
as one of those with Alva um and uh you
know I think nuclear right you know as a
base load is you know fabulous thing
that we want to go build more of. You
know, unfortunately, all of our
renewables have, you know, deep
dependencies in China, which is very
unfortunate uh you know, for us. You
know, we're, you know, uh, you know, gas
turbine lead times are only eight years
at this point, right? So, you know, you
know, I mean, we really have a difficult
environment to scale up rapidly, but
one, we just need more capacity. Yeah.
And fundamentally energy capacity
somewhat dampens how euph fork we can
get on AI, right? Because you know why
build a new data center and buy, you
know, the million GPUs if I can't power
them, right? And I think you're going to
see more and more defaults happening on
many of those data center projects
because the energy won't be there.
>> So you think it'll be a significant
headwind?
>> I think it will be a headwind and I
think you're already starting to see
some of the first indicators of that.
the Oracle, you know, uh, comet, you
know, was just I and I think that's the
first of what you're going to see many.
Now, it's not like we're going to slow
down as a result, but I think people
will start saying, do I really have the
energy, you know, to underwrite the
capital commitments that I'm making, you
know, for, you know, cement for data
center racks and, uh, GPU purchases. So
I do think it's you know going to be a
you know an upper bound
>> but we need more energy capacity and we
need to get more innovation into that
and we need more of those supply chains
in the US you know nuclear one of my
favorites you know when was the last
nuclear reactor that came online in the
US right you know it's 20 years ago
>> right you know we just stopped you know
a very capable uh industry so that's one
we need more uh you know we need to get
much more efficient at delivering you
know the power networks and as you you
know, moving 800 volt DC data centers.
Absolutely. You know, right, you know,
and being able to eliminate so many
conversion steps along the way because
of uh of uh uh historical uh you know,
reasons and you know, standardization
reasons. Okay, we got to fix this. You
know, an 800 volt DC, the revenge of
Edison is upon us.
>> Yes, I was just going to say,
>> yeah, I like to say so, you know, I do
think that ends up being we need better
power conversion. You know, we have a
couple of companies, one of those
vertical, you know, vertical GAN, you
know, I think will be, you know, a
killer technology, you know, to be able
to do 800 to 48 or 800 to 12 or even 800
to 5 in one conversion step, right?
Which just gives you a lot more uh
energy, you know, we touched on
>> solid state transformers, you know.
>> Yeah. You know, all of those are, you
know, solid state transformers,
switches, etc., you know, rebuilding,
you know, the power delivery network.
And I think that will, you know, have a
lot of, you know, innovation, you know,
it's sort of like, okay, power's cool
again, right? You know, you know, for
it. And then you're going to need all of
those in the cooling systems as well,
right? You know, and so there'll be a
bunch of innovations and that, you know,
so you know, you know, turbines and
refrigerants and, you know, all of a
sudden they get to be, you know,
exciting new technologies again. So, you
know, for all of us hardware guys, this,
you know, this, you know, is like
renaissance in front of us. It's just
going to be
>> after 25 years. I had to go back and
read about car's car
>> carinal efficiencies. Oh yeah. Is it
like good stuff? How does that first law
of thermodynamics work again?
>> Something after all here,
>> you know. So, so it's going to be you
know exciting time that way you know but
you know you know we also say you know
we need to change the physics right
because cos hasn't improved you know the
essential power per terror you know
power per teraflop for the last five uh
generations of Nvidia chips you know
flatline not okay right and that's where
some of the things you know we have a
superconducting company snowcap right
which affords the opportunity to
fundamentally change the physics you
know a thousand times better power
performance. So, I do think some of
those innovations are upon us in the
near future as well.
>> I've been a terrible time manager here
for the past hour. So, so many topics
yet to cover. We didn't cover, but we
got to cover at least one before we
leave.
>> Okay.
>> Because now
>> you're in charge.
>> Yes. So, I thought
um
now VMs are back.
>> How do you think about that as a former
CEO of VMware?
>> Well, you know, I I uh I feel excluded
from this conversation obviously if we
go on
>> part of it was I was going to talk about
networking as well so but I don't think
we have the time
>> you know hey you know I I think the you
know every innovation has always led to
the next abstraction right and I think
many of these ideas and you right you
know I always like to say you know you
know what's what's new in our world
today you know data structures
algorithms you know an abstraction you
know you know we bring it back to those
you know foundationals and hey you know
I you know the virtual machine
abstraction you know whether it's done
from the infrastructure level or from
the application level you know I think
it's still a foundational abstraction
model you know that deserves to always
have a place uh in the compute hierarchy
so you know so what do you think one of
us go back and run VMware again
>> yeah that's what I tell I think I told
it's time to go back and run VMware
again
>> yeah yeah and uh you know and I do think
some of these abstractions you know but
you also think about it and like one of
the things we did at VMware where we you
know essentially you know managed every
aspect of the computing hierarchy.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. You know and you manage the
workload, you manage the network, you
manage the storage you know system and
how do you abstract those? And I think
in the AI context, right? We think about
you know these agent swarms. Well, who's
going to manage the agents? Who's going
to create the security profiles around
all of the agents? Who's going to be
manage the performance of the agents?
You know, essentially every fundamental
element of virtualization and management
needs to get recreated in this next
computing hierarchy and there's going to
be lots of wonderful companies that
you'll sort of break through for how
those things will be, you know, done.
>> Okay. Do you want to end it on
networking?
>> Actually, I'd love to stay with the the
VMs for a second. And the most
interesting thing for me is that we're
now building VMs so that they're usable
for agents as opposed to usable for
humans. What we've seen in sort of other
companies is that that changes a lot the
form factor that changes a lot how you
market them, right? You want you want
the agent to make the pick for for for
your VM offering.
>> Um it it changes a lot how much
complexity you can have. It changes how
how quickly the startup should be.
Humans are a lot more patient than than
agents.
>> Um
>> so it's
if you have to rebuild VMware today, how
would it look different?
>> Yeah. And and I do think
>> like the VMware for agents.
>> Yeah. And I and I do think there's, you
know, does there need to be a VMware for
agents for humans, right? You know,
>> I see what you mean. Yes.
>> Right. You know, in the sense that, you
know, I need humans.
>> Let's stick to the agents. They're way
more interesting than right now.
>> Yeah. But, but, you know, I think it's
an important point because I do think
that there needs to be, you know, and
I'll use, you know, Dario's
constitution, right, or guard rails,
right? Or being able to set policies.
And I think then you you really say okay
every aspect of the virtual machine as
we know we'll love it today it is
servicing agents
>> right as opposed to servicing hardware
and humans right so I think you know
that becomes your fundamental design
constraint on this side you know how do
I make agents great
>> right how can I make them secure how can
I make them performant you know you know
uh you know how do I abstract them how
can I migrate them all of those things
you know have the new embodiment you V
motion for agents right it's like every
one of these will have the new
embodiment you know for them but then I
also need to think about how can humans
be setting the policies describing the
constitutions you know getting the you
know dashboards uh etc and I think
that's sort of you know where the
interesting thing is because you need to
do both of those right not just one of
those but the fundamental you know I'll
say the hard design stuff like we did
for you know virtual machines was
associate abstracting the hardware in a
performant way for applications or
operating systems here. It's, you know,
abstracting the hardware and the
operations for agents. It's a
fundamental thing that you're serving.
It
>> was great discussing this and thank you
so much, Pat, for coming in and we'll do
it again.
>> Well, two of my favorite people.
Anytime.
>> All right. Thanks.
>> That was awesome. Thank you.
>> Thank you.